Finding Aid for School of Art & Design (University of Michigan) records, 1947-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Art & Design (University of Michigan) records, 1947-2006 1947-2010, 1981-1999
University of Michigan. School of Art & Design.
830 MB
1 oversize volumes
7.0 linear feet
93824 Bimu C676 2
The first classes in art at the University of Michigan were offered in 1906 by the Department of Architecture. In 1926, a program in decorative arts was housed in the College of Engineering and Architecture. Art evolved as a discipline, moving through the colleges of engineering and architecture to become the School of Art, an autonomous institution, in 1974. It became the School of Art & Design in 1996. The records focus on the evaluation and review of the program in the 1970s and early 1980s during the budget crisis faced by the university. The records also contain minutes of the Executive Committee and the Faculty Committee, from the mid-1970s to 1999.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records were received in various accessions beginning in 1992 (donor 7510 ). The last accession was received in 2008. 7510
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The School of Art & Design records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy.
The School of Art & Design record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Executive Officer Records -- Boxes 3-7
The origins of the School of Art can be traced back to classes taught in design by Emil Lorch in 1906 in the Department of Architecture. Thereafter, classes were added in drawing, with an emphasis on naturalism, followed by courses in painting. Originally, classes in art were aimed at students majoring in architecture, but as time passed, more and more non-architecture students enrolled in the various classes. In 1926, a program in decorative arts was housed in the College of Engineering and Architecture. After a faculty member conducted a survey in 1939 of art instruction at other universities, "the former emphasis on academic theory gave way to a more direct and creative approach in the content, method, and objectives of courses and their sequences; this was reflected in the appointment of new staff members with a more modern realistic point of view." (Encyclopedic Survey, Volume III, p. 1309) Classes in sculpture were added in 1949. In 1954, the differences in the teaching of art and architecture were formally acknowledged when art received departmental status in the College of Architecture and Design.
The post-World War II boom in students led to a doubling in size of the art faculty between 1954 and 1960. The Bachelor of Fine Arts and Master of Fine Arts degrees were established in 1959, and a program in Medical and Biological Illustration in 1964. Areas of concentration grew to include painting, printmaking, sculpture, photography, ceramics, weaving and fabric design, and jewelry and metalwork. The steadily increasing number of students resulted in a shortage of physical facilities, which eventually led to the construction of a new building to house both art and architecture on the university's North Campus. In 1974, the Department of Art became the School of Art, and, along with the College of Architecture and Design, moved into the new building.
The School of Art faced its most serious crisis in 1982. As part of budget reducing measures in response to the financial crisis it faced, the university chose the schools of art, education, and natural resources to be reviewed for continuation or discontinuation. All three schools were continued, but with significant budget reductions. The School of Art budget was reduced by 18 percent.
The school was renamed the School of Art & Design in 1996, to better reflect the scope of the work. Its mission is to "educate and train artists and designers, to inform and influence others through the creation and dissemination of original ideas and visual work, and to provide a research environment that supports collaboration, integration of emerging technologies, and intellectual, and visual inquiry of the highest quality." (http://www.umich.edu/~provost) The graduate level interdisciplinary program in medical and biological illustration was one of only five in the nation accredited by the American Medical Association.
Deans of the School of Art and Design
1974 - May 31, 1984 George V. Bayliss
July 1, 1984 - December 31, 1985 Wendel W. Heers (acting)
January 1, 1986 - August 31, 1991 Marjorie Levy
September 1, 1991 - 1993 John H. Stephenson (acting)
July 1, 1993 - 1999 Allen J. Samuels
1999- Bryan Rogers
The School of Art & Design records are composed of six series: Topical Files, 1970-1987; Committees; Correspondence; Topical Files, 1980-2000; Visual Materials; and Website. There is a separate collection of printed material. The majority of the records document the years from 1975 to 1999, a crucial period in the school's history as it was formally established as a school in its own right and later experienced serious budget reductions.
Subjects:
Art.; National Association of Schools of Art and Design (U.S.); University of Michigan--Evaluation.; University of Michigan. School of Art.; University of Michigan. School of Art & Design.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Art and Architecture Building (University of Michigan); Demonstrations.; Protest movements.; Student movements--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Students--Political activity.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. School of Art & Design.
Genre Terms:
College publications.; Photographs.
- Topical Files 1970-1987
  The Topical Files, 1970-1987 series (1.8 linear feet) comprises the initial collection of material prior to the 2008 accession. (A second Topical Files series, cover 1980-2000 and consists of material received in the 2008 accession). The Topical File series is arranged alphabetically. The history of the department/school from 1951-1974 can be found in the History- Encyclopedic Survey folder. For the years 1975-1985, the administrative, pedagogical, and intellectual life of the school can be traced through several files. The materials in the evaluation and planning files were prepared as part of a university-wide project, begun in 1973 and undertaken in response to the budget crisis of the 1970s. The project was designed to improve the processes by which the university evaluated its activities and programs, established priorities, and allocated its resources. The project had three phases: phase I, articulation of unit objectives and operations implications; phase II, evaluation of operations in light of objectives described in phase I; phase III, exploration of directions and alternative courses of action. The files here include faculty responses to phase I questionnaires regarding the goals and objectives of the school and reports and conference summaries. The records document the school's participation in phases I and II, but not in phase III. The National Association of Schools of Art (NASA) files include informative Self Study Reports prepared by the school in preparation for visiting NASA accreditation teams. The reports detail school objectives and goals, its organizational framework, financial resources, physical environment, curriculum, and student and faculty relationships. Finally, the Review files from 1982-1983 include the review committee's final report, which explores the quality and mission of the school in some detail. Clippings on student protests, and materials documenting the work of the Transition Team, which was responsible for finding ways to implement the recommended 18 percent budget reduction conclude the series.
  - Annual Report to the President 1971 (Box 1)
  - Arts Legislation 1975-1983 (Box 1)
  - Budget
    - Correspondence 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Request for Incremental Appropriations 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Statistics 1982-1985 (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1975 (Volume 1)
  - Courses
    - Degree Requirements 1971-1985 (Box 1)
    - Description and Conversion 1947-1984 (Box 1)
    - Pass/Fail system 1972 (Box 1)
  - Documentation of Mokume-Gane (faculty grant application) 1980 (Box 1)
  - Evaluation and Planning
    - General 1974-1977, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Phase I Questionnaire and Responses 1976, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee 1981-1986, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Faculty Meetings 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Future of the Arts at the University 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - History
    - General 1970-1976 (Box 1)
    - Encyclopedic Survey, undated (Box 1)
  - Manhattan Project 1977-1982 (Box 1)
  - National Association of Schools of Art (NASA)
    - Accreditation
      - Annual Reports 1974-1976 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1976-1983 (Box 1)
      - Reports 1966, 1977 (Box 1)
      - Self Study Report (Evaluation Report) 1966 (Box 1)
      - Self Study Report 1977 (Box 1)
    - Ad hoc Planning Group 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - Outside Evaluation Team (Herron School of Art) 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - President's Correspondence 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Personnel undated (Box 1)
  - Press Releases 1972-1982 (Box 1)
  - Report on the Graduate Program to the Executive Committee of the School of Art September 1987 (Box 1)
  - Reunions undated (Box 1)
  - Review (Box 2)
    - General 1982 (Box 2)
    - Alumni Employment List 1982 (Box 2)
    - Board of Regents, Presentation to 1983 (Box 2)
    - Budget Reduction Proposal undated (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1982-1983, undated (Box 2)
    - Faculty Professional Career highlights 1982 (Box 2)
    - News Clippings 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - Press Releases 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - Public Meeting of Executive Officers 1983 (Box 2)
    - Rackham Graduate Issues Forum 1982 (Box 2)
    - Report on the School of Art 1982 (Box 2)
    - Review Committee (Box 2)
      - General 1982, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Charge 1982 (Box 2)
      - Report of the Subcommittee to Review the School of Art 1982 (Box 2)
      - Report
        - Abstract 1982 (Box 2)
        - Factual Material 1982 (Box 2)
    - Statistical Information
      - General 1982 (Box 2)
      - College of Architecture and Design Building Equipment Listing undated (Box 2)
    - "Stellar Reputations Issue," 1983 (Box 2)
    - Student Protest (news clippings) 1983 (Box 2)
    - Transition Team
      - General 1983-1984 (Box 2)
      - Basic Studio Report 1984 (Box 2)
      - Faculty Early Retirement 1984 (Box 2)
      - Faculty Governance Committee 1984 (Box 2)
      - Graduate Assistants 1984 (Box 2)
      - Transition Plan 1983-1984 (Box 2)
      - Transition Program
        - Section I undated (Box 2)
        - Section II 1983 (Box 2)
        - Section III 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - Visiting Artists 1983 (Box 2)
  - Space Planning 1986 (Box 2)
- Committees 1976-1999, 2004-2006
  The Committees series (1.0 linear feet, 1974-2006) contains records of two main committees: Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, and Faculty Committee Meeting Minutes. The Executive Committee Meeting Minutes cover the years 1978 to 1999. The records include the official meeting minutes and supplementary materials that pertain to the meeting discussions. It also includes lists of committee members from 1976 to 1999, for many different committees. The Faculty Committee Meeting Minutes cover the years 1974-2006 (with some gaps, particularly 2000-2004). The records also include the official meeting minutes and supplementary materials that pertain to the meeting discussions. There is more supplementary material for the later dates. Meetings also included announcements for exhibitions and talks.
  - Committee Assignments 1976-1999 (Box 3)
    [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2020 ]
  - Executive Committee Minutes
    - 1978-1998, 3 volumes (Box 3)
    - 1998-1999, 1 folders (Box 3)
  - Faculty Meetings
    - Minutes 1974-1999, 4 volumes (Box 3)
  - Faculty Council Meetings
    - 2004-2006 (Box 3)
- Correspondence 1997-1999
  The Correspondence series (0.2 linear ft, 1997-1999) contains five folders of correspondence of Dean Allen Samuels. This is a very fragmentary run of correspondence, but represents the whole of what was transferred.
  - Dean Allen Samuels 1997-1999, 5 folders (Box 4)
- Topical Files 1980-2000
  The Topical Files, 1980-2000 series (1.0 linear feet) contains an alphabetically arranged collection of topical files transferred in 2008. Many of the files contain publicity material about the school and individual faculty, including exhibition publications, newspaper clippings, and magazine articles. Faculty represented includes Vincent Castagnacci, Janet Leonard, Ted Ramsay, and Jon Rush. A 1992 North Campus Sculpture Plan is include as is a file with photograph of the sculpture by George Ricky at the Gerald Ford Presidential Library. Some early 1990s files detail transition plans and oversight of the school.
  - Alumni and Faculty, miscellaneous clippings and programs circa 1980-1990 (Box 4)
  - Alumni Exhibitions 1993-1997 (includes photos and slides) (Box 4)
  - Commemorative Bas Relief for "Center of Champions," 1989 (Box 4)
  - Faculty
    - Clippings and Publicity (Al Hinton and others) (Box 4)
    - Castagnacci, Vincent 1979-1996 (Box 4)
    - Leonard, Joanne 1979-1996 (Box 4)
    - Ramsay, Ted 1975-1999 (Box 4)
    - Rush, Jon 1978-1989 (Box 4)
    - Sato Pijanowski, Hiroko 1980-1999, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - North Campus Sculpture Plan 1992 (includes negatives) (Box 4)
  - Ricky, George, (Sculpture at Gerald R. Ford Library. Includes 3 black and white photographs and twelve color slides) 1982 (Box 4)
  - School of Art Oversight Committee 1991 (Box 4)
  - School of Art Position Papers 1989 (Box 4)
  - Transition Plan with 1991 responses, 1984, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Undergraduate Program Initiative 2000 (Box 4)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series (3 linear feet, ca. 1975-2001) contains the majority of the most recent addition to the record, and is arranged alphabetically. The series is comprised of 35 mm slides, photographic prints and negatives. Images date from 1975 to 2001, and document faculty work, art classes, exhibits, and other school events. There are several folders of interest in this series. The Student Protests folder, which was part of the original accession, has images of an organized protest against proposed budget cuts to the School of Art in the early 1980s. The Francoise Gilot folders contain images of visits by the famed artist, author, and former companion of Pablo Picasso to the School of Art in the 1990s. Also note that many images of faculty or their work are included in the Faculty (miscellaneous) folder, rather than individual folders. The Visual Materials series also contains seven boxes and a binder of slides of faculty work and classroom images. The slides are arranged by category. The categories can be found in the box content listing.
  - Photographs and Negatives
    - Alumni Event 1988-1993, undated (Box 5)
    - Andrews, Benny undated (Box 5)
    - Art and the Natural World Exhibit 1998 (Box 5)
    - Bahnmiller, Carol 1990 (Box 5)
    - Bamboo, Cynthia 1983 (Box 5)
    - Bangert, Shaun 1999 (Box 5)
    - Barrett, William undated (Box 5)
    - Becker undated (Box 5)
    - Boykin, Heather 1997 (Box 5)
    - Building and faculty group photographs 1983-1997, undated (Box 5)
    - Campus 1975-2000 (Box 5)
    - Carter, Carol Ann undated (Box 5)
    - Castagnacci, Vincent undated (Box 5)
    - Ceramics Course undated (Box 5)
    - Cheng, Mignonette Exhibit Opening undated (Box 5)
    - Computers for Artists Course undated (Box 5)
    - Conference on Education and Environment 1989 (Box 5)
    - Cressman, Larry 1992 (Box 5)
    - Curry, Stephen undated (Box 5)
    - Davis, Linda undated (Box 5)
    - Davis, Phil 1988 (Box 5)
    - Design Course, undated (Box 5)
    - Donahue, Kevin undated (Box 5)
    - Drawing Course undated (Box 5)
    - Faculty (miscellaneous) circa 1993-1996 (Box 5)
    - Faculty Shows 1999, undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Fibers course circa 1994 (Box 5)
    - Fort, Nancy undated (Box 5)
    - Forum and African Art 1992 (Box 5)
    - Freshpeople 1992 (Box 5)
    - Fungs, Henry 1992 (Box 5)
    - Gibson, Mike 1992 (Box 5)
    - Gilot, Francoise 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Gordon, Mark 1992-1993 (Box 5)
    - Graduate Students 1992 (Box 5)
    - Graduation 1992-1999, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - Grigely, Joseph 1996 (Box 5)
    - Hay, Beth 1993-1994 (Box 5)
    - Higby, Wayne undated (Box 5)
    - Hinton, Al undated (Box 5)
    - Hodge, Gerry undated (Box 5)
    - Industrial Design Course undated (Box 5)
    - Inzuka, Sadashi circa 1996 (Box 5)
    - Jackson, Shaun 2001 (Box 5)
    - Jacobsen, Carol 2000 (Box 5)
    - Japanese Packaging Exhibit 1987 (Box 5)
    - Krecic, Mark undated (Box 5)
    - Kurusaki, Akira 1995 (Box 5)
    - Lahti, Aaron 1993 (Box 5)
    - Leonard, Joanne circa 1986-1988 (Box 5)
    - Levy, Marjorie undated (Box 5)
    - Lewis, Bill 1993 (Box 5)
    - Loving, Al 1989 (Box 5)
    - Luchs, Kathryn undated (Box 6)
    - Lutz and Hilton Show 1987 (Box 6)
    - McGaw, Wendy 1989 (Box 6)
    - Mame, (negatives) 1989 (Box 6)
    - Manupelli, George undated (Box 6)
    - Marinaro, Lou 1993 (Box 6)
    - Master of Fine Arts (MFA) Shows 1992-1993 (Box 6)
    - MCampaign 1992 (Box 6)
    - Medical Illustration Course 1988 (Box 6)
    - Metals Course undated (Box 6)
    - Miller, Dennis 1996 (Box 6)
    - Mixed Media/Alternative Processes Course 1992 (Box 6)
    - Martin Luther King (MLK) Day undated (Box 6)
    - Morgan, Clarence 1993 (Box 6)
    - Naney Great Lakes Exhibit 1992 (Box 6)
    - National Cathedral 1996 (Box 6)
    - Ozlesko, Pat undated (Box 6)
    - Pijanowski, Eugene 1989 (Box 6)
    - Porter, Marianetta 1996 (Box 6)
    - Ramsay, Ted 1983 (Box 6)
    - Robbins, Warren 1996 (Box 6)
    - Rush, Jon, (includes blueprints, newspaper clippings) circa 1981 (Box 6)
    - Samuels, Allen circa 1999 (Box 6)
    - Seika University 1996 (Box 6)
    - Smith, Sherri 1984-1989 (Box 6)
    - Stephenson, John 1983-1995 (Box 6)
    - Student Protests 1985 (Box 6)
    - Student work (miscellaneous) 1992-1999 (Box 6)
    - Takahara, Takeshi circa 1985-1992 (Box 6)
    - Zirbes, Georgette circa 1980-1995 (Box 6)
  - Slides
    - Slide Box 1 circa 1974-1999
      - School of Art Building-Interior (Box 6)
      - School of Art Building-Exterior (Box 6)
      - Gallery Openings (Box 6)
      - Bus (Box 6)
      - Art Museum (Box 6)
      - Art Office (Box 6)
      - University Campus (Box 6)
      - University Cellar-Lounge (Box 6)
      - University Campus (Box 6)
    - Slide Box 2 circa 1977-1983
      - 2D (Box 6)
      - Aqueous Media (Box 6)
      - Ceramics (Box 6)
      - Art Education (Box 6)
      - Drawing (Box 6)
      - Color (Box 6)
    - Slide Box 3 circa 1970-1999
      - Drawing (Box 6)
      - Design (Box 6)
      - Graphic Design (Box 6)
      - Fibers (Box 6)
      - Interiors (Box 6)
      - Industrial Design (Box 6)
      - Metals (Box 6)
      - Medical Illustration (Box 6)
      - Lettering (Box 6)
      - Interiors (Box 6)
    - Slide Box 4 circa 1969-1982
      - Painting (Box 6)
      - Sculpture (Box 6)
      - Printmaking (Box 6)
      - Photography (Box 6)
      - Sculpture (Box 6)
      - Visualization (Box 6)
    - Slide Box 5 circa 1977-1989 (Box 7)
      - Students at Work Ceramics (Box 7)
      - High School Workshop Fall 1981 (Box 7)
      - Students at Work
        - Drawing (Box 7)
        - Interior Design (Box 7)
        - Industrial Design (Box 7)
        - Graphic Design (Box 7)
        - General (Box 7)
      - Printmaking (Box 7)
      - Photography (Box 7)
      - Painting (Box 7)
      - Jeweler and Metals (Box 7)
      - Weaving (Box 7)
      - Watercolor (Box 7)
      - Sculpture (Box 7)
    - Slide Box 6 circa 1979-1989
      - School Programs and Faculty (Box 7)
      - Andrews (Box 7)
      - Bayliss (Box 7)
      - Bruden (Box 7)
      - Carter (Box 7)
      - Cogswell (Box 7)
      - Cheng (Box 7)
      - Cervenka (Box 7)
      - Castagnacci (Box 7)
      - Cassara (Box 7)
      - Hesseltine (Box 7)
      - Heers (Box 7)
      - Davis (Box 7)
      - Larkin (Box 7)
      - Kersten (Box 7)
      - Kamrowski (Box 7)
      - Hodge (Box 7)
      - Mullen (Box 7)
      - Montalvo (Box 7)
      - McClure (Box 7)
      - Marinaro (Box 7)
      - Lewis (Box 7)
      - Leonard (Box 7)
      - D. Lee (Box 7)
      - Lee (Box 7)
      - Larson (Box 7)
    - Slide Box 7 circa 1978-1989
      - Rush (Box 7)
      - Rieder (Box 7)
      - Ramsay (Box 7)
      - Pijanowski (Box 7)
      - Pallazzola (Box 7)
      - Olson (Box 7)
      - D. Smith (Box 7)
      - Sears (Box 7)
      - Samuels (Box 7)
      - Sadler (Box 7)
      - S. Smith (Box 7)
      - Weber (Box 7)
      - Stewart (Box 7)
      - Stephenson (Box 7)
      - Snyder (Box 7)
      - Zirbes (Box 7)
    - Slide Binder (Faculty Slides) circa 1975-1989 (Box 7)
- Archived Website
  The Archived Website series (830 MB, 2002-2008; 2010- ) documents the academic programs, accomplishments, resources, events, and people at the School of Art & Design. Content includes important news and announcements, publications (such as newsletters and course catalogs), and information about admissions, curriculum, degree requirements, faculty, exhibits, and the overall mission of the School. The website series is arranged chronologically and includes content captured by the Internet Archive starting in 1997 as well as captures provided by Bentley Library archivists 2002, 2003, 2006, and 2008. Starting in 2010, this archived website will be captured on a regular, ongoing basis as part of the University of Michigan Web Archives, hosted at http://webarchives.cdlib.org/a/universityofmichigan/.
  - School of Art & Design
    - 1997-2001
      (These versions were preserved by the Internet Archive and are made available through its Wayback Machine. The Bentley Historical Library is not involved in the collection or maintenance of this material.)
    - 2001-ONGOING
    - March 28, 2002, .ZIP file
    - May 21, 2003, .ZIP file
    - February 23, 2006, .ZIP file
    - April 30, 2008, .ZIP file
    - 2010-ONGOING
  - Related resources
    - 2010-ONGOING
Related Material
For materials related to the early history of the teaching of art, the researcher is advised to consult the following collections and record groups also at the Bentley Library:
University of Michigan. College of Art and Urban Planning records
Emil Lorch papers
Wells Bennett papers
Philip Youtz papers
Additional material on the 1983 review can be found in the records of senior executive offices such as Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs, and President